SOPHIA CHAN

sophia_chan@mymail.sutd.edu.sg | +65 92327839 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/sophiasychan/ | https://sophiasychan.github.io/Portfolio/

PROFILE

Singaporean PhD graduate with a strong background in chemistry and biochemistry fields focused on improving biosensor sensitivity and therapeutic efficiency. Extensive experience in integrating highly specialised fields such as chemistry, bioengineering and bioinformatics for multi-disciplinary research projects.

EDUCATION

Singapore University of Technology and Design

Doctor of Philosophy (Science and Math Cluster), GPA: 4.67/5.00

Jan 2017 - Jan 2022

The University of Edinburgh

Master's of Science (Chemistry with Industrial Experience), First Class Honours

Sep 2011 – Jun 2016

EXPERIENCE

NovogeneAIT, Singapore

Scientific Application Specialist

Mar 2021 - Present

- Responsible for processing customer samples on and off site, and validating new methods of DNA and RNA extraction
- Communicating, contributing and collaborating with Marketing and Sales departments locally and globally to increase revenue and awareness of services
- Kept detailed records of experimental protocols and inventory

Singapore University of Technology and Design, Singapore

PhD Research

Jan 2017 - Jan 2022

- Led 4 research projects concurrently to develop a sensitive electrical-based cancer biosensor, identifying and optimising issues by adopting creative solutions within tight deadlines
- Consolidated and organised research findings into internal weekly progress reports, 2 first-author peer-reviewed manuscripts and communicating research work at 3 international conferences
- Maintained various mammalian cell cultures, developed experimental protocols, analysed results with 99% accuracy, while keeping accurate records and complying with health and safety regulations
- Supervised 2 junior PhD candidates, contributed to and supported internal projects and collaborated with external researchers across different fields
- Managed and maintained lab equipment and consumables, updating records of inventory in a detailed manner

A*STAR (Bioinformatics Institute), Singapore

PhD Research Project

Sep 2017 – Dec 2017

- Collaborated with a team of 3 to design a molecular dynamics simulation protocol to understand the molecular interactions between 2D materials and cancer lipid bilayers,
- Results were consolidated into 2 published peer-review manuscripts
- Learned and utilised GROMACS and visual molecular dynamics (VMD) software to analyse the interactions

University of Edinburgh (Lusby Group), Scotland, UK

Master's Research Project

Sep 2015 - Feb 2016

- Designed and developed a new protocol to synthesise an organic ligand for pH-stable supramolecular cages for drug delivery
- Partnered with a team of 4 researchers to analyse the ligand, troubleshooting issues to improve the protocol
- Experimental protocol and insights were submitted as a Master's Thesis

Nippon Telegraph and Telecommunications (NTT) Basic Research Laboratories, Japan

Internship Project

Jun 2014 – Jun 2015

- Collaborated with a multi-functional team of 6 Japanese and English speaking researchers to realise a neural labon-chip device
- Findings were consolidated into a submitted Project Report

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Chan, S. S. Y. Chan, Go, S. X., Meivita, M. P., Lee, D., Bajalovic, N., Loke, D. K., <u>Ultra-efficient highly-selective MCF-7 cancer cell therapy enabled by combined electric-pulse carbon 1D-nanomaterials platforms</u>, *Mater. Adv.*, (2022) DOI: 10.1039/D1MA01118A

Chan, S. S. Y. Chan, Lee, D., Meivita, M. P., Li, L., Tan, Y. S., Bajalovic, N., Loke, D. K., <u>Ultrasensitive Two-Dimensional Material-Based MCF-7 Cancer Cell Sensor Driven By Perturbation Processes</u>, *Nanoscale Adv.*, **3**, 6974-6983 (2021)

Chan, S. S. Y. Chan, Tan, Y. S., Wu, K. X., Cheung, C., D. K., <u>Ultra-High Signal Detection of Human Embryonic Stem Cells Driven by Two-Dimensional Materials</u>, ACS Appl. Bio Mater, 1, 210-215 (2018)

SELECTED CONFERENCES

Chan, S. S. Y. Chan, Lee, D., Meivita, M. P., Li, L., Tan, Y. S., Cheung, C., Bajalovic, N., Loke, D. K., Highly Sensitive One-dimensional Material-based Biosensor for Residual Cancer Cell Detection, 2021 MRS Fall Meeting and Exhibit, Boston, MA, USA/Virtual, Dec 2021

Chan, S. S. Y., The Road Towards Safer Stem Cell Therapies, Research Fest 2019, Singapore SG, Jan 2019

Chan, S. S. Y. Chan, Tan, Y. S., Wu, K. X., Cheung, C., Loke, D. K., Two-dimensional Materials that Enhance Human Embryonic Stem Cell-signal Detection, ACS Spring 2019 National Meeting and Exposition, Orlando, FL USA, Apr 2019

SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

Best Flash Talk, Research Fest (Top speaker for a 3 min presentation out of 20 participants)

2019 2017

Rigel Technology Graduate Research Competition Award, FIRST Industry Workshop (Top 8 posters) out of 58 posters)

SKILLS

Experimental: Mammalian cell culture (stem cells, cancer cells, epithelial cells), nanomaterial fabrication and characterisation (SEM, UV-vis spectra, FTIR, IR), electrical characterisation, conductive polymer film fabrication, analytical characterisation (immunostaining, cell viability assays),

Computational: Data analysis, Python3, GROMACS, visual molecular dynamics (VMD), modelling, MS Office (Word, Excel, Powerpoint) and computer literate,

General: Scientific writing, scientific presentation, good presentation skills, lab maintenance, management and organisation, teaching, mentoring, highly motivated, great collaborator, multi-task